Guide to the Hubert Bradford Vickery Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Hubert Bradford Vickery papers
1796-1978
1928-1977
MS 875
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5
The papers contain correspondence, unpublished writings, and research material relating to Hubert Vickery's work as a biochemist at the Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station. Because reprints and drafts of publications have not been retained, there is little documentation of his experimental results in the papers. There are, however, details of his major contributions to establish a system of notation for amino acids and also to record the histories of their discovery. The papers also contain genealogical materials, including legal and financial papers of the Bradford family of London and the Starr family of Nova Scotia, and memorabilia from the atomic tests on Bikini Island.
Vickery, Hubert Bradford, 1893-1978
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jeannette Opsahl, 1979.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings. III. Project Files. IV. Personal Papers.
Biographical / Historical
Hubert Bradford Vickery was born in Yarmouth, Nova Scotia on February 28, 1893. He received both his B. Sc. (1915) and his M. Sc. (1918) from Dalhousie University and his Ph.D. from Yale University in 1922. He was appointed assistant biochemist, Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, 1922-1928, biochemist in charge, 1928-1963, emeritus biochemist, 1963-1978. From 1924 to 1963, he taught as a lecturer at Yale University. In 1946, he was an observer at the Bikini Island atomic bomb tests. Vickery was an active experimentalist on the organic acids and proteins in plants whose successful efforts resulted in more than 200 publications in biochemical journals. He died on September 27, 1978.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain correspondence, unpublished writings, and research material relating to Hubert Vickery's work as a biochemist at the Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station. Because reprints and drafts of publications have not been retained, there is little documentation of his experimental results in the papers. There are, however, details of his major contributions to establish a system of notation for amino acids and also to record the histories of their discovery. The papers also contain genealogical materials, including legal and financial papers of the Bradford family of London and the Starr family of Nova Scotia, and memorabilia from the atomic tests on Bikini Island.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Amino acids -- Nomenclature; Biochemistry; Botanical chemistry; Operation Crossroads, Marshall Islands, 1946; Plant physiology; Biochemists; Bradford, George Adams; Vickery, Hubert Bradford, 1893-1978; Bradford family; Starr family; Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station
- Correspondence, 1928-1977; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence is primarily professional in nature. The letters are arranged alphabetically by name of the individual, professional organization, or journal. Vickery's major contribution to the establishment of nomenclature for amino acids is documented in the correspondence with the National Research Council Division of Chemistry and Chemical Technology, Committee on Nomenclature. Correspondence in Series III, Project Files, also traces Vickery's work on the nomenclature and the history of amino acids. The Plant Physiology, the Journal of Biological Chemistry, the Biochemical Preparations and the Journal of the American Chemical Society correspondence documents Vickery's efforts as a reviewer as well as a contributor to the journals.
  - A, 1929, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Science, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Chemical Society. Committee on Nomenclature, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Society of Plant Physiologists, 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Analytical Biochemistry, 1962-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Analytical Chemistry, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual Review of Plant Physiology, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - B, 1935, 1942-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bade, Maria, 1962-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Becker, Stanley L., 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Biochemical Preparations, 1945-1968 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - C, 1931, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cahn, R. S., 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chibnall, A. Charles, 1963-1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Citric Acid Cycle, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cohn, Waldo E., 1963-1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, 1955-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - D, 1932, 1964-1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Dalhousie University, 1965-1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Dictionary of Scientific Biography, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - E, 1965-1975 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Encyclopedia of Chemical Technology, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - F, 1929-1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - G, 1968-1975 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - H, 1947-1975 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Hanson, Kenneth R., 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Hirschmann, Hans, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - I, 1955-1975 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ihde, Aaron J., 1960-1971 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Industrial and Engineering Chemistry, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - J, 1950-1957 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Journal of Biological Chemistry, 1932-1972 (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
  - Journal of the American Chemical Society, 1950-1972 (Box 2, Folder 38-39)
  - Journal of the History of Medicine and Allied Sciences, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - K, 1965-1973 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - L, 1966-1974 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - M, 1928, 1965-1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - N, 1966-1975 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - National Academy of Sciences
    - General, 1959-1973 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Biographical Memoirs [William Mansfield Clark], 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - National Research Council. Division of Chemistry and Chemical Technology. Committee on Nomenclature, 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 47-54)
  - National Science Foundation, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - O, 1926-1975 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - P, 1956-1975 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Palmer, James K., 1964-1973 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Plant Physiology, 1953-1972 (Box 4, Folder 59-61)
  - R, 1965-1975 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851, 1929-1977 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - S, 1930-1974 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Science, 1962-1970 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Steward, F. C., 1962-1970 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - T, U, V, 1956-1976 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - W, Y, Z, unidentified, 1939, 1966-1977 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - W. B. Saunders Company, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 69)
- Writings, 1930-1973; Series II
  This series is composed of drafts and notes for invited lectures, papers presented at professional meetings, reports, unpublished papers, and a 1964 autobiographical essay. The papers are arranged chronologically. Reprints and draft copies of Vickery's many published papers have not been retained. Bibliographic listings of Vickery's publications are filed in Series IV. George W. Pucher, a co-worker at the Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, is mentioned as co-author on several papers.
  - "Some Aspects of the Chemistry of Green Leaf Cells", 1930 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Stephen Hales Prize [acceptance speech], 1932 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Protein Metabolism of Tobacco Leaves" [read at meeting of American Society of Plant Physiologists], 1933 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Recent Ideas of Protein Structure" [lecture at Columbia University], 1933 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "The Effect of Heavy Fertilization with Ammonia on the Glutamine Content of Beets" [read at meeting of American Society of Plant Physiologists], 1934 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "On Glutamine" [in collaboration with George W. Pucher and Harold E. Clark], 1935 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Protein Chemistry in Relationship to Cell Physiology" [lecture at New Jersey Experiment Station], 1935 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Proteins" [lecture at Middletown, CT], 1935 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "The Biochemistry of the Amides in Plants" [lecture, Rochester section of American Chemical Society], 1937 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "Preparation of the Basic Amino Acids" [contribution to Dunn's Biochemical Preparations ], 1937 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Report to R. H. Manske of the study of roots of Corydalis ochotensis Turez, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "Amide Metabolism in Green Plants" [Sigma Xi lecture], 1938 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - "Protein Metabolism in Leaves" [lecture for Pre-medical Club, Wesleyan University], 1938 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - "The Construction and Use of the Widmark Extractors for Liquid Extractions" [with George W. Pucher], [194-] (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - "A New Method for the Determination of Glutamine in Plant Tissue" [with George W. Pucher], [194-] (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - "The Influence of Samuel W. Johnson on the Chemistry of Proteins" [lecture, Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station], 1940 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - "Liebig and the Chemistry of Proteins" [lecture], 1940 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - "The Work of Thomas B. Osborne" [lecture, Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station], 1940 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - "End Products of Nitrogen Metabolism in Plants" [paper, Society of Biological Chemists], 1941 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - "Liebig and Proteins" [read before New England Association of Chemistry Teachers], 1941 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - "Plant Proteins" [read at Chemistry Department Seminar, Stanford University], 1941 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - "The Origin of the Word Protein" [correspondence, notes], 1941-1953 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - The Chemistry of the Amino Acids [book review], 1944 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - "The Proportion of Histidine Yielded by Human and Bovine Serum Albumin and Fibrin" [report], 1944 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - "The Proteins of Soy Beans" [report to National Research Council], 1944 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - "Suggested Program for Research on Soy Bean Protein", 1944 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - "The Atomic Bomb Tests at Bikini" [notes, correspondence], 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - "L-Asparagine Monohydrate" [with George W. Pucher], 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - "The Relationship of the Sheffield Scientific School to Agriculture" [address at centennial celebration], 1947 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - "The Metabolism of Organic Acids in Plant Leaves" [lecture at Northwestern University], 1948 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - "Organic Acids of Leaves" [seminar], 1948 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - "Perspectives and Personalities in Protein Chemistry" [lecture], 1948 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Proteins and Amino Acids in Nutrition [book review], 1948 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - "The Personalities of Protein Research", 1949 (Box 6, Folder 34-35)
  - "The Early Work of Osborne and Mendel in Nutrition" [lecture], 1950 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - "Chemical Changes in Connecticut Shade Grown Tobacco During Curing and Fermentation" [lecture], 1951 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - "The Metabolism of Organic Acids in Plant Leaves" [lecture for the National Research Council], 1951 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Symposium on Nitrogen Metabolism in Plants [remarks as chairman], 1952 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - The Chemical Structure of Proteins [book review], 1954 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - "A Statistical Method for the Collection of Identical Samples of Plant leaves" [correspondence], 1956-1973 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - "The Origin of the Word Protein" [lecture], 1957 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - "The Significance of Organic Acids in the Tobacco Leaf" [lecture], 1957 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - "The Significance of Organic Acids in Tobacco Leaf" [paper], 1957 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - "Crassulacean Malic Acid" [lecture ], 1958 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - "The History of Phosphotungstic Acid as a Reagent in Amino Acid Chemistry" [lecture], 1961 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - "The Metabolism of Glutamic Acid in the Tobacco Leaf" [lecture], 1963 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - "Autobiographical Notes", 1964 (Box 6, Folder 48-50)
  - "The Origin of the Experiment Station Idea", 1968 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Principles of Biochemistry [book review], 1968 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - "How Crops Grow" [lecture], 1969 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - "The Origin of The Connecticut Experimental Station", 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - "Samuel W. Johnson, Father of Agricultural Science in America" [lecture], 1970 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - "The Contribution of Carl Wilhelm Scheele to Protein Chemistry", 1972 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - "d-Isocitric Acid", undated (Box 6, Folder 57)
- Project Files, 1926-1978; Series III
  This series is composed of correspondence and notes that are organized by topic and that relate to Vickery's scholarly endeavors. The series contains detailed information on Vickery's efforts to revise the nomenclature for amino acids in 1961. It also documents his abiding interest in the history of the discovery of amino acids. The Connecticut Agricultural Experimental Station files include ideas for research as well as notes on possible publications. The Yale University folder contains materials relating to the lecture courses Vickery taught from 1924 to 1963, including some examination questions.
  - Amino acids
    - General, 1928, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Nomenclature, 1970-1978 (Box 7, Folder 2-7)
  - Anderson, Rudolph John, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station [research problems for investigation], 1929-1961, undated (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
  - "The History of the Discovery of Amino Acids II"
    - Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Notes, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Notes, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - "Schultze, E.'s Anticipations of What Were Later Discoveries of Others in Protein Chemistry" [notes], 1937-1943 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Yale University [course materials], 1926-1959 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Personal Papers, 1796-1973; Series IV
  This series includes memorabilia, photographs, and materials relating to Vickery's family. Genealogical information about Vickery's forbears, including the Bradford and Starr families, and clippings about family and friends in Nova Scotia are included. The memorabilia is composed of souvenirs collected by Vickery as an observer of Operation Crossroads, the nuclear bomb detonation at Bikini Atoll in 1946. Photographs include a few images of Vickery, as well as portraits of professional colleagues and pictures from Operation Crossroads.
  - Bibliography, 1922-1971 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1932-1973, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Family estate papers, 1796-1841, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    General note
    See also: Oversize, folder 1.
    See also: Oversize folder 1
  - Genealogical materials
    - Charts, 1903-1963, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
      General
      See also: Oversize, folder 2.
    - Correspondence, 1904-1964, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Printed matter, 1914- 1964, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Memorabilia
    - General, 1937-1972 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      See also: Oversize, folder 3.
    - Bikini Atoll observation, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
      See also: Oversize, folder 4.
    - Honorary degree [at Sheffield centennial celebration], 1947 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Photographs
    - General, 1915-1965, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Bikini atomic bomb tests, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 12-14)
      See also: Oversize, folder 5.
- Oversize, 1796-1973
  - Family papers, 1796, 1832 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Genealogical charts, 1940, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Memorabilia
    - General, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Bikini Island atom bomb tests, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 5)